<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>Hayden Church's blog</title>
<description>A blog about movies</description>
<link>https://htchurch.xyz/rss.xml</link>
<atom:link href="https://htchurch.xyz/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<language>en-us</language>
<item>
    <title>Pi</title>
    <link>https://www.htchurch.xyz/blog#26</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.htchurch.xyz/blog#26</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>So rough-edged and clearly Aronofsky's first film even if you hadn't been told that ahead of time, <em>Pi</em> (or π if you like) is also his best film, part schizo-collage like <em>Requiem for a Dream</em> but also the first to feature one of his mentally ill obssessives who push it too far like in <em>The Wrestler</em>, <em>The Black Swan</em>, and, I guess, <em>Noah</em>. Of course the film's subtle critique of Jewish paranoia is provoking, but it's at the cost of the film's worst move: <em>Pi</em> rudely conflates religious wonderment with mental frailty. In the end we're not supposed to see any order in the world — it's all random, allegedly — and nothing means nothing. Aronovsky never really evolves from there, does he?</p>]]> </description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Hitchcock Kills Dad</title>
    <link>https://www.htchurch.xyz/blog#25</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.htchurch.xyz/blog#25</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>I wrote about <em>The Lodger: A Story of the London Fog</em> (1927), <em>Shadow of a Doubt</em> (1943), and how Hitchcock kills dads at <a href="https://apocalypse-confidential.com/2021/04/11/hitchcock-kills-dad/">Apocalypse Confidential</a>.</p> ]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Postcolonial Re-imaginings in Touki Bouki</title>
    <link>https://htchurch.xyz/blog#24</link>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">https://htchurch.xyz/blog#24</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[ <p>The French New Wave finally made its way to Africa in the late 1960s, thanks in part to the French postcolonial presence on the African continent, which gave rise to the particularly influential artistic output of directors in Senegal, with films like Djibril Diop Mambèty's <em>Touki Bouki</em> (<em>Journey of the Hyena</em>, 1973). Though originally a commercial flop, and previously only available on low-quality VHS releases, <em>Touki Bouki</em> was one of the first films restored in 2008 by Martin Scorcese's <a href="https://www.film-foundation.org/world-cinema">World Cinema Project</a>, which &quot;preserves and restores neglected cinema from around the world.&quot; Now in streaming format on the <a href="https://www.criterion.com/films/28412-touki-bouki">Criterion Channel</a>, we can all see Mambèty's brave film in a modern context.</p>
<p>Mambèty's nonlinear tale shows two college students, Mory (Magaye Niang) and Anta (Mareme Niang), as they scheme to steal some money, but after that plan fails, the two wander (and wonder) aimlessly around postcolonial Senegal. Repeating shots and spatial incongruities form Mory and Anta's fantasy landscape as they attempt to break free from their colonial consciousness. The real daring of Mambèty, though, is in his stark refusal to be a propagandist.</p>
<p>Past critics have noted that <em>Touki Bouki</em> represents an aesthetic counterpoint to what is called Third Cinema, postcolonial cinema best represetned in film's like Gillo Pontecorvo's <em>The Battle of Algiers</em> (1966) and Ousmane Sembène's <em>Black Girl</em> (1966) — two films with explicitly revolutionary politics, their aims toward anti-capitalism and, ultimately, decolonization.</p>
<p>In <em>Touki Bouki</em> Mambèty's filmmaking is, in fact, ambiguously political. He rebelliously refuses to make the sort of political statemetns that in many ways defined Francophone African cinema. This not to say, of course, that Mambèty is apolitical; certainly, the images of violent animal bloodletting (such as when cattle are slaughtered and a goat's throt is slit) and the film's famous bull-horns, Mambèty's images of fate, say otherwise. The representation of left politics in the film, signified by a group of hostile revolutionaries who hassle Mory and Anta, shows total defiance toward an African intellectual elite.</p>
<p>That's because Mambèty's goals in <em>Touki Bouki</em> weren't unequivocally political. Using the road genre, a love story about two university students, Mambety's camera syncretizes two different cultural practices — the aural and the aural-visual — into a distinctly African style of filmmaking that recontextualizes them both.</p>
<p>More recently, <em>Touki Bouki</em> has entered the public consciousness, through its appropriation by billionaire-millionaire artists Jay-Z and Beyoncé. In 2018, the couple recreated an iconic image of the film — with the film's protagonist on their fledgling motorcycle with mounted bull-horns — for the <em>On the Run II</em> tour (June-October 2018). Like Mory and Anta, whose daydreams blend fantasy and reality in postcolonial Senegal, Beyoncé and Jay-Z's recreation hoped for a diasporic effect, suggesting they, too, are runaways.</p>
<p>In one scene, Anta and Mory pull a heist; they steal a wealthy gay man's gay, nabbing some of his clothes, too (he calls the police and flirts with the investigator). The joyride takes place on an empty road, heading into town. Mory emerges, naked, on top of the car, and begins a hostile-yet-not-angry speech. In it, Mory declares victory over all his foes, real or not, describing in detail how he wrestled his way to the top. Intercutting the sequence are shots of children running alongside the car. But the camera reaveals that these children are a fantasy, Mory's imagined audience. The result is that the scene is an astonishingly great act of myth-making.</p>
<p>The stolen car, painted in red, white, and blue, provides Mambèty perhaps his most daring image of rebellion, an image that not only re-contextualizes an African storytelling tradition called Griot in postcolonial France but also reminds the audience of an American and British colonial past. Mory's naked oration mixes personal fantasy with colonial history, an appropriation of oppressive symbolism that now provides, at least for a moment, the feeling of freedom — pre-Oedipal plenitude — where anything and everything is possible.</p>
<p>Mory's griot, though certainly not a strictly tradition griot performance, nevertheless syncretizes the Senegal tradition with a then-contemporary postcolonail subject's desires — a representation of what scholars David Murphy and Patrick Williams call in African postcolonial cinenma the <em>griauteur</em>, a hybridization of the African (griot) and Western (auteur) storyteller. As the film intercuts the car sequence with the children sequence, he creates a mythos of victory — of conquering through wrestling — with masculine self-assurance. It's a distinctly African sequence, transformed by both histories of European colonialism and technology. Mambèty's filmic equivalent bring African tradition to European film and European film to African tradition.</p>
<p>Mambèty's daring in this scene reveals the importance of that kind of brazen, naked freedom that many Americans are afraid of, let alone reflected back at them onscreen. Mambèty's hybrid style is, on its face, typical of the categorizations applied to African filmmakers whose styles combine the West with the Global South; yet his execution and craftsmanship, his awareness of both African and European filmmaking styles, is nevertheless unique.</p>
<p>To be sure, he never makes overt political statements, unlike his contemporaries. For the viewer, however, Mambèty's understanding of the postcolonial situatino, its politics and cultural impact, is deeply intuitive and instinctual. Now, at least, we can all appreciate Mambèty's cheekiness.</p>
<p><em>Originally published at Popmatters on November 4, 2020</em></p>
 ]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>